A Guide to the Gertrude E. Perlmann papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA189
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Conferences; meetings; seminars, 1949-1974
  - New Hampton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Proteins, 1961 June 26-30 (Box 17, Folder 29)
    [Indications Perlmann attends but no presentation].
    Includes program; list of participants; correspondence; Konigsberg et al ms; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Moscow Vth International Congress of Biochemistry, 1961 August 10-16 (Box 17, Folder 30)
    Typescript of abstract "Molecular structure and biochemical activity".
    Includes correspondence; general information.
    [Planned to attend but cancelled].
  - London, St. Mary's Hospital Medical School Antibody Workshop, 1961 August 30-September 1 (Box 17, Folder 31)
    Includes program; hotel correspondence.
  - New York Academy of Science Symp. on "Antibody to Enzymes - A three-component system", 1962 September 5-7 (Box 17, Folder 32)
    Typescripts of Arnon and Perlmann-paper and abstract "Antibodies to pepsinogen and pepsinogen modifications".
    Includes correspondence; programs; Cinader reprint; Perlmann/Arnon work outline Published in 1963. See #54 in bibliography.
  - NY City RI lecture "Discussion of group work", 1963 March 12 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Includes typescript and handwritten outline of discussion.
  - NY City Columbia University Biophysics Graduate Student seminar Handwritten outline of seminar, 1963 March 15 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Palo Alto, Calif. Standford University Symposium on Quantum Aspects of Polypeptides and Polynucleotides, 1963 March 25-29 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Typescripts "Comments on correlation between fluorescence, optical rotation and biological activity" and discussion; includes correspondence; duplicated material of Symposia information; program; participants. Published in 1964. See #56 in bibliography.
  - [Location?] American Chemical Society Meeting, 1963 May 10 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    Handwritten outline of "Biochemical Discussion".
  - Cold Spring Harbor Symposium on Quantitative Biology on Synthesis and Structure of Macromolecules, 1963 June 7-13 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Perlmann attends June 8 morning session [No evidence of presentation] Correspondence; program.
  - Meriden, NH at Kimball Union Academy. Gordon Conference on "Cell Structure and Metabolism", 1963 June 17-21 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Correspondence; general information; program; summary of paper by J.D. Bernal; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - New Hampton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Proteins, 1963 June 23-28 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    Includes general information; program; group photograph of participants with photo identification.
  - London, England. Oxford meeting of Biochemical Society, 1963 July 20 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    Typescripts "Relation of protein conformation to biological activity" and abstract.
    Includes correspondence; slide outline.
  - NY City 124th Electrochemical Society meeting, 1963 October 2 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    Typescripts "Entropy of conformational changes in enzymes" and abstract. Abstract published in 1963. See #55b in bibliography.
  - [Location, Institution?], 1963 October 9 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    Handwritten outline of talk on protein research - phosphoproteins and pepsin-pepsinogen with slide outline.
  - [Location - Institution?] Rel. Prot. Conf. - Enzyme activities in pepsin-pepsinogen [from original file folder], 1963 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    Typescripts "of current laboratory work".
  - NY City Columbia University Chemistry Dept, 1964 February 11 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    Graduate student seminar.
    Typescript "on current laboratory work".
    Includes handwritten outline.
  - Brookhaven Nat'l Laboratory Symposium on subunit structure of proteins, 1964 June 1-3 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    Correspondence; program; visitor information; participants; expenses.
  - NY City 6th International Congress of Biochemistry, 1964 July 26-August 1 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    Correspondence; duplicated material.
  - Tilton, New Hampshire, Gordon Research Conference on Biopolymer-solvent interactions and the structure of liquids, 1964 August 2-7 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    Duplicated material includes: participants, program, general information; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Woods Hole, Mass. 19th Annual meeting of Society of General Physiologists on Molecular Architecture, 1964 September 9-12 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    Correspondence; duplicated material of general information.
  - Storrs, Conn. University of Conn, seminar Typescript "Relation of protein conformation to biological function. The pepsinogen-pepsin system", 1964 October 1 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    Includes correspondence; handwritten outlines of presentation and slides.
  - RU student seminar, 1964 December 16 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - San Francisco, 9th Biophysical Society meeting, 1965 February 26 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    Typescript "Medium and temperature effects on the titration of the basic amino acid residues of pepsinogen.
    Includes photocopied figures.
    Abstract published in 1965. See #58b in bibliography.
  - [Month? Location?] American Society of Biological Chemists meeting, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    Typescripts Koehn, Oestreicher and Perlmann paper and abstract "Structural studies on pepsinogen".
    Abstract published in 1965. See #58a in bibliography.
  - 1965 Mar. 19 NY City New York Academy of Science, Iota Sigma Pi meeting (Box 18, Folder 21)
    Typescript "Studies on protein structure".
  - New Hampton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Proteins, 1965 June 28-July 2 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    Correspondence; duplicated material includes: program, list of participants; other duplicated material on equipment and nomenclature; Perlmann handwritten notes; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Woods Hole, Mass. [No further information], 1965 August (Box 18, Folder 23)
    Typescript "Optical rotatory properties of the phosphoprotein phosvitin".
  - Atlantic City, N.J. 150th ACS meeting (American Chemical Society) Garvan medal symposium, 1965 September 14 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    Typescript of abstract "Anatomy of a protein molecule; includes correspondence. [Garvan award lecture typescript "Anatomy of a protein molecule" see under: Biographical material - Garvan Award in Box no. 1].
    Abstract published in 1965. See #58c in bibliography.
  - Boston, Mass. 10th Biophysical Society Meeting, 1966 February 25 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    Typescript of Perlmann and Allerton paper and abstract "Optical rotatory dispersion of phosvitin".
    Includes photographs of tables and figures possibly used for slides.
    Abstract published in 1966. See #62a in bibliography.
  - Atlantic City, N.J. Annual meeting of the American Society of Biological Chemists, 1966 April 15 (Box 18, Folder 26)
    Typescript of Gournaris and Perlmann paper "Succinylation of pepsinogen".
    Includes correspondence; photocopy of abstract.
    Abstract published in 1966. See #62b in bibliography.
  - Providence, R.I. Brown University seminar, 1966 May 6 (Box 18, Folder 27)
    Typescript "Pepsin-pepsinogen current laboratory work".
    Includes handwritten slide outline.
  - New Hampton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Proteins, 1966 June 27-July 1 (Box 18, Folder 28)
    Correspondence; duplicated material includes: program, participants, transportation information; Science reprint on Conferences; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Tilton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Physics and Physical Chemistry of Biopolymers, 1966 August 1-5 (Box 18, Folder 29)
    Correspondence; costs; duplicated material includes: participants, travel instruction, program; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Vienna 2nd International Biophysics Congress, 1966 September 5-9 (Box 18, Folder 30)
    Typescripts of Perlmann, Oplatka and Katchalski, A. paper and abstract "Conformation changes of pepsinogen derived from potentiometric studies".
    Includes correspondence; printed material on general information; duplicated material on Congress time table and program. Correspondence indicates Dr. Perlmann acts as Chairman of session "Proteolytic and other enzymes".
    Abstract published in 1966. See #62d in bibliography.
  - NY City 152nd meeting of the American Chemical Society, 1966 September 12 (Box 18, Folder 31)
    Typescript of Ong and Perlmann abstract "Specificity of insoluble trypsin" Abstract published in 1966. See #62c in bibliography.
  - NY City RU student seminar, 1966 November 16 (Box 18, Folder 32)
    Typescript of report on current laboratory work.
  - Madras, India International Symposium on "Conformation of biopolymers", 1967 January 19-21 (Box 18, Folder 33)
    Typescript "Conformational patterns and their relation to biological activity".
    [Perlmann cancelled due to lack of travel funds].
    Includes correspondence; program; participants; visa application for India.
  - Israel lecture Typescript "pepsin-pepsinogen", 1967 April (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - Chicago, Ill. FASEB meeting, 1967 April 16-21 (Box 18, Folder 35)
    Typescripts of Rimon and Perlmann paper and abstract "Carbamylation of pepsinogen" [probably presented by S. Rimon].
    Includes typescript Eng Bee Ong abstract "Inactivation of pepsin by a diazomethyl ketone of N-benzylorycarbonyl-l-phenylaline" with working draft of abstract. Indicates Dr. Ong attends meeting.
    Abstract published in 1967. See #68a in bibliography.
  - Waltham, Mass. Brandeis University lecture, 1967 June (Box 18, Folder 36)
    Typescript on pepsin-pepsinogen work.
  - Tokyo, 7th International Congress of Biochemistry, 1967 August 19-25 (Box 18, Folder 37)
    Typescripts of paper and abstract "Structural studies on pepsinogen and pepsin".
    Includes correspondence. Published in 1967. See #63a in bibliography. Also abstract typescript "Optical rotatory properties of succinyl-pepsinogen" not presented but published with abstracts of 7th International Congress of Biochemistry. Not listed in bibliography.
  - Milwaukee, Wise. [Institution?] Typescript of current laboratory work, 1968 January (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - NY City RU seminar, 1968 March 1 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Typescript "Studies on the structure and function of pepsinogen and pepsin" with slide outline and information sheet to RU Calendar of Events.
  - Atlantic City, N.J. FASEB 52nd meeting, 1968 April 15-20 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Typescript of Ong and Perlmann abstract "The amino terminal sequence of porcine pepsinogen".
    Includes printed informational material relating to meeting [Attendance not clear].
    Abstract published in 1968. See #71a in bibliography.
  - New Hampton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Proteins, 1968 June 24-28 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Correspondence; duplicated material includes: program, participants, regulations and general information; Perlmann handwritten notes; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Tilton, NH Gordon Research Conference on Physics and Physical Chemistry of Biopolymers, 1968 August 26-30 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Correspondence; duplicated material includes: travel instructions, regulations and general information.
  - Copenhagen, Denmark, Alfred Benzon Biochemical Symposium on "The Role of Nucleotides for the Function and Conformation of Enzymes", 1968 September 9-11 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Correspondence; program; list of participants.
  - Baltimore, Md. [Institution?] seminar, 1968 November 26 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Typescript "pepsin-pepsinogen laboratory work" with slide outline.
  - [Month, Day?] Holyoke, Mass. Mt. Holyoke seminar, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Typescript "current laboratory work" with slide outline.
  - Seattle, Washington seminar, 1969 February 24 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Typescript "on current laboratory work" with slide outline.
  - La Jolla, Calif. Biophysical Society meeting, 1969 March 3 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Typescript "on current laboratory work"; handwritten outline of presentation; slide outline.
  - NY City New York Medical College seminar, 1969 April 2 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    1 item correspondence indicates Perlmann gives presentation.
  - Copenhagen, Denmark, International Symposium on structure-function relationships of proteolytic enzymes, 1969 June 16-18 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Includes correspondence; program and symposium information. Typescripts of presentation and abstract (published abstracts of Symposium included) "Pepsinogen-pepsin" with slide outline; photocopied typescript of published paper "Porcine pepsinogen and pepsin".
    Published in 1970. See #73 in bibliography.
  - NY City 158 meeting of the American Chemical Society. Second Symposium on "Ordered Fluids and Liquid Crystals", 1969 September 10-12 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    Includes correspondence; Symposium program.
    Typescripts of presentation and abstract "Phosvitin, a phosphoprotein with polyelectrolyte characteristics"; typescript of Perlmann and Grizzuti paper "same title".
    Published in 1970. See #74 in bibliography.
  - Atlantic City, N.J. FASEB Annual Meeting, 1970 April 12-17 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    Nakagawa and Perlmann "Reduction and reoxidation of pepsinogen and pepsin".
    Abstract published in 1970. See #76a in bibliography.
    Includes correspondence; typescript drafts; slide outline; summary of presentations; photographs of figures and tables.
  - Copenhagen, Denmark lecture, 1970 August (Box 19, Folder 15)
    Typescript "Phosvitin, a phosphoprotein from hens' egg yolk"with slide outline.
  - Interlaken, Switzerland, 8th International Congress of Biochemistry, 1970 September 3-9 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    Typescripts of presentation and abstracts Effect of substrate binding on the conformation of porcine pepsin" with slide outline, handwritten figure and table.
    Includes correspondence; programs.
  - Boston University School of Medicine, Department of Biochemistry seminar, 1971 January 28 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    Typescripts "Phosvitin, a phosphoprotein from hens' egg yolk. Chemical conformational and biological properties" with slide outline.
  - San Francisco, Calif. Federation meeting of American Society of Biological Chemists, 1971 June 14-18 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    [Perlmann section chairman - Section Proteins, Structure].
    Typescript of Wong, Nakagawa and Perlmann abstract "Gossypol reaction sites of pepsinogen".
    Abstract published in 1971. See //81a in bibliography.
    Includes also typescripts of R. Shainkin abstract and presentation; R. Wong presentation; correspondence.
  - Meriden, NH Gordon Research Conferences on Proteins, 1971 July 19-23 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    Correspondence; program; participants; travel information; photocopy of Klotz and Darnall published ms; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Santa Barbara, Calif. 1st Gordon Conference on the Chemistry and Physics of Liquid Crystals, 1972 January 17-22 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    Typescript "Optical properties of phosvitin and phosvitin-polyamine complexes".
    Includes correspondence; duplicated material includes: program, participants, general information folder; slide outline.
  - London, Ciba Foundation Symposium on Polymerization Reactions in Biological Systems, 1972 March 14-16 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    Perlmann participant in Discussion.
    Includes typescript of part of discussion; printed symposium program and synopses of papers; duplicated material concerning Symposium.
  - Atlantic City, N.J. FASEB Annual Meeting, 1972 April 9-14 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    Typescript of Finlay and Perlmann paper "Mechanism of the gossypol inactivation of pepsinogen"; also photocopy of abstract.
    Abstract published in 1972. See #84a in bibliography.
    Includes correspondence; printed material on meeting. [Dr. Perlmann plans to attend but cancels].
  - Plymouth, NH Gordon Research Conferences on Chemistry and Physics of Biopolymers, 1972 July 3-7 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    Correspondence; printed material on conference [Dr. Perlmann plans to attend - cancels due to fractured leg].
  - Chicago, Ill. 13th Nat'l meeting of APhA, '. Academy of Pharmaceutical Sciences Symposium on Liquid Crystals, 1972 November 5-9 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    [Perlmann invited to present but correspondence. indicates declines, no evidence of attendance].
    Correspondence; duplicated material on Symposium.
  - 3 lectures [no other information], 1972 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    Includes typescripts of Perlmann presentations with slide outlines on pepsin-pepsinogen and phosvitin work.
  - Sanibel Island, Fla. International Research Workshop and International Symposium on Atomic Molecular and Solid State Theory and Quantum Biology, 1973 January 14-27 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    [Perlmann invited to attend as a special participant but declines].
    Correspondence; duplicated material on Workshop and Symposium.
  - Tucson, Arizona, University of Arizona, The Graduate Program in Biochemistry seminar, 1973 March 9 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Correspondence indicates Perlmann presentation "Phosvitin, a phosphoglycoprotein. Chemistry, conformation and biological function".
    Typescript "Phosvitin, a phosphoglycoprotein from hen's egg yolk" with slide outline, photographs of figure and table.
  - Albuquerque, N.M. University of New Mexico, Department of Biochemistry, School of Medicine seminar, 1973 March 14 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Atlantic City, N.J. FASEB Meeting, 1973 April (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Proteins: Conformations II session.
    Typescript (Photocopy) of Finlay, Dharmgrongartama and Perlmann abstract.
    Abstract published in 1973. See #89a in bibliography,.
    Includes program of Apr. 17 session with list of speakers and presentations with photocopies of their abstracts.
  - Austin, Texas University of Texas seminar Title of presentation not known, 1973 May 6 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Correspondence indicates Dr. Perlmann visits College Station, Texas, Texas A & M Univ. after Univ. of Texas seminar.
  - Birmingham, Alabama, University of Alabama, Institute of Dental Research seminar Perlmann presentation "Phosphoproteins", 1973 May 23 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence; seminar announcement; 4 Perlmann reprints.
  - Stockholm, Sweden, 9th International Congress of Biochemistry, 1973 July 1-7 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    Typescript of abstract "Conformational transition of the phosphoglycoprotein phosvitin".
    Abstract published in 1973. See #89b in bibliography.
    Includes correspondence; printed material concerning Congress.
  - Chicago, Ill. 3rd American Chemical Society Symposium on Ordered Fluids and Liquid Crystals, 1974 August 26-31 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Typescripts of Grizzuti and Perlmann paper and abstract "The binding of divalent ions to the phosphoglycoprotein phosvitin".
    Abstract published in 1973. See #90 in bibliography.
    Includes correspondence; photographs of slides and working copy of paper; program; printed abstract instructions.
    [Correspondence indicates Dr. Perlmann attends Women Chemists luncheon on Aug. 27].
  - Santa Barbara, Calif. 2nd Gordon Research Conference on The Chemistry and Physics of Liquid Crystals, 1974 January 14-18 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    Typescript "Relation of the binding of divalent ions to optical and hydrodynamic properties of phosvitin".
    Includes correspondence; duplicated material on general information, program, participants, travel information; group photograph of participants with identification.
  - Nutley, N.J. Roche Institute of Molecular Biology seminar, 1974 March 28 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    Typescript "Phosvitin, chemistry, conformation and biological properties" with slide outline.
    Includes correspondence.
  - Jamaica, NY St. John's University seminar Typescript "Relation of the binding of divalent ions to optical and hydrodynamic properties of phosvitin", 1974 March 29 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Rehovath and Kibbutz Ayelet Hashachar, Galilee, Israel 2nd International Symposium on Polyamino acids, polypeptides and proteins and their biological implications, 1974 May 2-7 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    Correspondence [Perlmann attends but no indication of presentation].
  - Minneapolis, Minn. American Society of Biological Chemists/Biophysical Society joint meeting, Biochemistry/Biophysics meeting, 1974 June 2-7 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    Perlmann - Chairman of Section Protein Structure I [Dr. Perlmann cancels due to ill health].
    Typescript of Marchaim, Altschul and Perlmann abstract "Characterization of a phosphorus-containing protein from methyl-cholanthrene-induced ascites tumor cells.
    Abstract published in 1974. See #90a in bibliography.
    Includes typescripts of all other abstracts of session on Protein Structure I. correspondence. includes workings as session chairman; duplicated material includes: instructions to chairmen, slide preparation and presentation.
  - Stockholm, Sweden 5th International Liquid Crystals Conference, 1974 June 17-20 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    [No indication of Perlmann attendance].
    Includes part handwritten, part typescript of a possible Perlmann paper.
  - Atlantic City, N.J. 168th American Chemical Society Symposium on phosphoprotein structure, 1974 September 9-13 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    Photocopied typescript "Conformational studies on the phosphglycoprotein phosvitin" of abstract.
    Abstract published in 1974. See #90b in bibliography.
- "Ueber santal pterocarpin und homopterocarpin, die farblosen begleiter des santalins. [No. 1 in bibliography same title (II Mitteil)] (Package 3)
- Manuscript materials
  Include Annual Scientific reports; working papers and laboratory notes. Publication information where possible.
  - Annual Scientific Reports, 1948-1974 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Lacks 1962/1967. Up to 1954/1955 Dr. Longsworth submitted final annual reports on G.E. Perlmann work. Beginning with 1955/1956 G.E. Perlmann submitted her own annual reports. Beginning with 1955/1956 G.E. Perlmann submitted her own annual reports.
    - 1948-1949
      Submitted by Dr. Longsworth
    - 1949-1950
      Submitted by Dr. Longsworth concerning Perlmann work
    - 1950-1951
      Includes outline; final report.
    - 1951-1952
    - 1952-1953
      Includes various typescripts; final report submitted by Dr. Longsworth concerning Perlmann work.
    - 1953-1954
      Includes typescript and handwritten reports. Submitted by Dr. Longsworth concerning Perlmann work.
    - 1954-1955
      Includes typescripts; laboratory notes. Final report submitted by Dr. Longsworth concerning Perlmann work.
    - 1955-1956
    - 1957-1958
    - 1958-1959
    - 1959-1960
    - 1960-1961
    - 1961-1962
      Includes handwritten draft describing S.E. Allerton work.
    - 1962-1967
      (lacking).
    - 1968-1969
    - 1969-1970
    - 1971-1972
    - 1972-1973
    - 1973-1974
      Includes working material; catalog laboratory work description.
  - H. Raudnitz and G.E. Perlmann, 1935 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Ueber santal, pterocarpin und homopterocarpin, die farblosen bergleiter des santalins (II Mitteil.) Berichte der deutschen chemischen gesellschaft 1862-1866.
    Typescript drafts with corrections.
  - Fritz Lipmann, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Metabolic generation and utilisation of phosphate bond energy. (Review of energy-rich phosphate bonds) npi (no publication information).
    Typescript draft with figures.
  - G.E. Perlmann, 1942 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    A crystalline protein from kidney cortex. (Ms sent to R.M. Ferry).
    npi (no publication information).
    Typescript draft.
  - G.E. Perlmann, 1943 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Shock experiments elec. data MGH [Massachusetts General Hospital] J. Aub [Description from file folder].
    Typescript and handwritten tables; typescript summary; figure in duplicate.
  - L.G. Longsworth, 1945 (Box 21, Folder 6)